[Music]
Tim thank you for coming we first got in
touch because of a shared interest in
Jordan Peterson
you wrote the first article for The
Spectator I think at about the same time
as I brought out my documentary and
Jordan Peterson last year and you also
have a really keen interest in Alan
Watts and a lot of people have made this
comparison that Jordan Pederson in some
ways is doing for Western religion what
Alan Watts did for Eastern religion back
in the 50s and 60s I think it's a really
interesting topic to explore do you
think it's a good comparison well also
Alan Watts demystified Christianity I
mean as Peterson is doing in that sense
he is a precursor of Peterson in other
words he tried to rethink the real
meaning of Christianity without any need
for magical thinking or you know he
wasn't religious in that conventional
sense you know that he thought there was
a great God watching us all you know he
was debunking debunking that idea and he
was trying to get at the deeper
questions of what the Bible was trying
to reach much often through the Gnostic
Gospels he would he would refer to as
Peterson does also that there is this
wisdom in the book you know that is
largely hidden from view by the church
you know much of the interesting things
about the Bible are kept out of sight
and I think in that sense he is he
certainly a precursor to Peterson in in
that he's involved in this great project
or what Peterson calls redefine the
substrate of the Western ideological
project if you're not ideological proper
philosophical project of individual
freedom and so forth and from what I
understand about the the Gnostics versus
the kind of Christian tradition is that
the Gnostics were about
livid experience of God so it's more of
an inner spiritual knowing is that I
don't know much about the Gnostics but I
do think that sounds about right and
that's what that's what what was about
you know he was about the immediate
present experience of your of your life
you know and about you know very much
emphasis on that this is one of the ways
he does differ from Peterson because
Peters and in a way is is all about
having a goal for the future and and
what's was not about that he was all
about saying that the future take care
of its self which I think he he quoted
Jesus about that you know care not for
the morrow consider that it is the field
it's section which he said this is never
really preached anymore you know because
it's a subversive message which is like
don't worry about tomorrow you know
you'll be fine
and that's quite quite contrary to the
sort of things that Peterson talks about
the fine enough I you know last time I
met Jordan Peterson I asked him that
very thing because I said well how are
you coping with all this pressure that
you're under and he said well you know I
just don't think about tomorrow I'm
constantly and I said what's a bit of
paradox isn't it you know is this and
then you know anything yeah but you know
it's any way I can get through it really
it's just blogged and living all the
present all the time so oddly enough you
know the idea there's something in both
of the ideas I mean they can both become
corrupted in a way you know if you if
you think of of thinking and living in
Peterson's goal-directed life you could
I think very easily find yourself stuck
in the future so psychologically and if
you lived
what's is non goal-directed life which
is kind of he was kind of anti goal I
think by nature of you know Zen Ness and
living in the now um you can get stuck
in that because I think that can be
quite a crisis I mean it's all very well
to live in the present but you know if
sort of slap someone the round face and
ten minutes later used to turn around
them so you're still going on about that
fall that was ten minutes ago you know
so it doesn't make much sense does it
so you know there's there's a place for
these things but but they're they're
both but what they have in common is
they're both brilliant brilliant
teachers whose minds and not merely
great minds but have great communication
skills that is quite rare you know for
somebody of that level of intelligence
to have such a flair for expressing it
and also both of them really are
interpreters you know that in some ways
they're not known certainly what's more
so than with them Pearson was not really
an original thinker he was just very
very brilliant extracting meanings from
other thinkers and other traditions and
Peterson to some extent no I think he's
um you know he's more of an original
thinker but he's you know he realized
very heavily on people like nature and
Solzhenitsyn but he does formulate I
think I'm Joseph Campbell but I mean I
think he he formulates a very coherent
understanding out of us of those sources
and moves them on I think in other words
he's discovery as he would put it of an
essential DNA of all the great stories
which is something people have been you
know edging towards ever since the
Golden Bough and and the for the Fraser
Book II think I think he moves out on a
very long way and I think he really he
really develops that theory of narrative
as a form of expressing things that we
cannot express yet by words which we
cannot conceptualize and that's not you
know it's what which is one of the
reasons are very interested in Peters
and Watts doesn't me talk about
narrative in that in that way so it's
not a big difference is I think Peterson
is is concerned with mythological
narratives
and what's his is not really his
interesting understanding what we can
learn from Eastern thought how it can be
combined with Royston religion and and
they're both Mavericks because they you
know they take a very radical view in
both cases not only of Christianity but
I mean in what's this case of Eastern
philosophy I mean he's he's philosophy
is very unlike other you know you read
about pieced and philosophers and Zen
you know it's all about sitting
cross-legged which he called the UM
aching back school of Zen
I think area so they he was he wasn't
even putting the interest in meditation
I mean oh they taught it I mean it
wasn't bothered you know so he was very
sort of he was very much of the you know
that's why I think he became more and
more of a Taoist as he went on because
he also he wasn't much into self
discipline which I think in Jordan Buzz
Peterson is on the point of their
differences and especially on the the
difference between Alan waters let go
and you know not worrying about the
future and Peterson's kind of goal
driven pick up your cross walk up the
hill take responsibility they were they
were both okay Peterson's popular now
what's also I think very much of his
time and place do you think those two
messages kind of fit into two different
cultural eras do you think what what's
was saying would have the same impact if
you were saying it now and I think
that's a very very astute point I think
they are products at their time you know
I may think what's came out of a time
when the culture was very uptight you
know and it was very you know who's very
much the yeah
the tyrant king was running things you
know and it was very authoritarian it
was very straight-laced I mean his peak
was in the 50s you know just before
nominee he was teaching through the 30s
40s and 50s I think he started in the
30s um but he was he was at a time when
that as it were the straitjacket that
had to be loosened was one of sort of
you know autocrat autocratic hype
controlling fearful psychology and her
now as it were he's take has been taken
to his absolute extreme and peace and is
as it were acting as the antithesis to
to bring it back to there to some
greater understanding again so I think
yeah you could see them once as two
poles of an underlying unity which would
be a very zen way of looking at you know
I know you describe yourself as an
atheist what is it about these two
figures that you find fascinating well
because I think there's a sense in which
they're both atheists a sense you know I
think with the word atheist is is is
laden with kind of I think first I am
I'm willing to use that word because I
immediately want to distance myself from
a you know dogmatic Christians and be
new-age idiots you know so I talked
about spirituality all the time I'm so
I'm very quick probably too quick to use
the word atheist and it's probably not
the right word because it it suggests a
Richard Dawkins kind of narrowness of
mind about these things you know I'm
certainly not put it this way I'm not a
scientific materialist I don't think you
just look at the world and what you're
seeing is just stuff you know I know
absolutely don't think that at all is a
very very mysterious element which is
revealed in science you know I didn't
lose a thing controversial
I mean when you look at quantum physics
and recent scientific discoveries to be
for it to be very plain that something
bloody weird is going on you know it's
not just the 19th 18th century view that
we're all sort of hard machines and
that's crazy
so when I say I'm a theist I mean I
don't believe you know that if I believe
in God this I will you know be rewarded
in heaven or in reward on earth
necessarily and if I say I'm you know an
atheist it doesn't mean that it means I
don't sort of you know if I see the
Buddha on the road I will kill him you
know so I think that's that's that sort
of idea but where there's not there's
not there's not kind of a word for how I
feel myself to be which is somewhere on
the margins of a belief in a great
mystery that's going on and there the
peculiarity of existence so I'm very
against I know it's not minute I'm not a
scientific materialist I hate scientific
materialism I think it's a destructive
stupid ideology that is largely
responsible for all sorts of problems
and in today's world it's given us a
great deal but also psychologically I
think it's been a very arid and
inaccurate way of looking at the world
and growing up as I did in the nineteen
fifties which is almost the high point
of you know scientific materialism which
really said this that he said if you
can't measure it doesn't exist that's
the scientific view or the scientific
materialism if you can't measure the
damned thing there it's it's a figment
of your imagination and that includes
consciousness it's like we can't measure
consciousness so there's no
consciousness it's an epiphenomenon
you're stupid
and that's just like saying yeah what
you know but you're thinking that how
come you're thinking that if it's just
that people now I mean is there it's
denying the most fundamental reality
that we have which is the inside of our
own heads which is our consciousness
there's no more fundamental
we are reality than that people say well
that's not real what the hell is real
you know if that's not real that's
ridiculous and that is kind of you know
things are all too common I think and
that's really the in as much as it's
thought about at all you might call it
the default view of this society it
strikes me just on that point that both
warts and Peterson have a strong
metaphysical element what they're saying
may be in different ways that I don't
know that's actually my question is are
they pointing even though they're taking
it from you know East and West and
ostensibly quite different are they
pointing to some similar metaphysical
reality do you think or is it different
you know I I don't know anymore than I
know about the nature of a metaphysical
reality you know I mean I suspect that
there is a metaphysical we arty now was
a reality beyond that which but I don't
know the nature of it you know I mean
and I don't know what it is and I don't
I can't you know I have a sense that
it's good in a way are they not both
pointing to the I mean you described as
a mystery there is a humility in in
Peterson I don't know what's quite quite
so well but I get a sense there's a
humidity and both of there so yeah
that's a really good point because what
it's about is is the acceptance of
uncertainty you know I mean I and
Peterson is very big on this assignee
you don't know anything you're very
small and the world is very big you've
got a whole of history before you the
whole of the future ahead of you and the
whole world around you and you're this
tiny little grunt you know have some
humility
what the hell do you know you know and
I'm what's is one what's his greatest
books was the wisdom of insecurity which
is really the same principle is saying
look you don't know
you know how humility in the face of the
mystery which is that in reality you
know things are very very hard to
understand and I suppose that's a
perception I've had with me since I was
quieter well as long as I can remember
he's like what the hell is going on and
why is everybody so down with it you
know
because it strikes me as bizarre and
perplexing and um and everyone else
doesn't seem to most people urgency to
register there and so they both speak to
me in saying you know life is ineffable
and unknowable so they're very much both
in the same camp now but it feels to me
like their response to that is different
because for what's and the more Daoist
response to that would be to surrender
into the unknowable mystery and your ego
isn't trying to control it
whereas peterson is saying to an extent
at least find meaning find
responsibility you know find some
directions and go in the future and I'm
not sure whether those things square
with each other I don't think those do
square with each other but I do think
that sort of walks you in a stroke
Eastern point of view is that you have
an essential inner wisdom that we don't
we don't use enough you know and and
that we need to acknowledge that
mysterious Center of ourselves
which which is the the heart of real
knowing as a piece I'm not sure except
that I would say that he does speak very
much about humility he speaks a lot
about how you know you have to the
beginnings of wisdom as the fear of God
the idea that you and and the and that
Satan was an intellectual and so forth
no idea that that the knowledge that you
possess is the beginning and the end of
the world is that you know the ultimate
sin of pride you know and and so
actually they are quite similar in that
because they're saying just understand
you know your place in things which is
at one level as what say you know there
is something godlike in you but you know
the human side of you is is woefully
inadequate you know I think I think
that's sort of yeah I think that's I
think it's interesting how what's to
wear how julen pleases was about how
your your pathetic little weasel
you know he's gotta this idea that
you're you're essentially in originated
this kind of original sinner idea that
you are just weak and and pathetic and I
think that would be quite alien towards
who is sort of you know much more this
sort of you know what's inside you is it
can be relied upon even though it can be
unreliable you know so so he you know he
wouldn't make the point as always trust
you know always trust your inner voice
he said you're in the position where you
have life is essentially to be in a
position of a gambler who is making bets
and there are no certain outcomes or or
a yachtsman who's trying to tack and and
sail through very unpredictable waters
you know so there's no clear way forward
and you have no guarantees of a good
outcome and I think now you know that
unlike religion which even even Buddhism
which says you know just meditation
you'll be everything will be beautiful
that's like really you know and and and
and Peterson likewise you know you can
go you know this is the this is your
best bet is to follow this path but it
doesn't guarantee anything you know it's
it's it you know you can still have
horrible bad luck and dreadful things
can happen to you and no one's
controlling those things it's just you
know it's just bad happens to
people and you can't control that so
this sort of yeah does there's an
element you know if you humility I
certainly think what's is more about as
you say letting go the need to control
things but there's an element of that I
think in Jordan Peterson too and more
and in a sense letting go the need to
know things in a strange way you know or
they need to know of your certainties
would you say there's more of a
utopianism in what's because with
Peterson he says you have to take a
poison or all you have is the choice of
which poison to take you have to take a
poison or as what there's a sort of
sense of maybe a bit more of a utopian
element to it I don't think is utopian I
think it's some
probably more optimistic you know I mean
I don't think he thinks there's some I
don't think he sees the utility of
sufferin perhaps that's in the way that
you know Jordan Peterson does he doesn't
necessarily think one should be beating
one selves up and it's probably nothing
you never probably know I did this P
doesn't be fair but I mean you know I
think there's there's not that's that
sort of sense you've got to go down as
the depths before you can emerge fully
formed
I think what's is just like just stop
trying so hard and you'll be all right
you know that's because some up is you
know just to stop straining you know to
do things and and what's was much
misunderstood at the time what's didn't
like that beatniks for instance you know
the whole Kerouac do what you feel type
of thing he's very much just disappeared
of that nonsense I thought it was just
very had a lesson really so yeah I think
I think there's there are differences
and there are similarities but I feel
that they were on the same path and what
had a lot of admiration for young even
though he didn't talk about it requires
as much as Jordan Peterson and maybe it
wasn't playing that same role of
reviving him to the culture but one of
one of my favorite lectures he talks
about young in the shadow in particular
and that striking is an interesting
point where they they meet because the
shadow is maybe one of the most popular
Union ideas that Peterson is bringing
back into the culture so I mean I don't
know I don't know much about Watson his
take on young but how much do you think
young kind of influences thinking or how
important was it not really aware of it
I mean you know it must have I mean you
know maybe there and if you've seen that
lecture but it hasn't stuck with me I've
sort of seen everything and listened to
everything that he's done so I can't
imagine it was a repeating motif I mean
I'd have to say I'd be very interested
to see that that sure but I don't you
know I don't remember he talked talks
about fraud
of course young was into Eastern
philosophy himself and and any and
that's why I didn't immediately think of
Yungas he frames it in those terms but
but actual facts the idea of there being
polarities within us you know which is
essentially that the Union was that
everything's opposing forces you know is
exactly what he I'm you said he's but
the book is all about you know the
polarities that that that are at working
inside the human psyche I know how much
this is referring to the question you
asked me her but it was what I was
thinking about while you were asking it
and it makes me think that this idea of
I don't know if balance is the right
word but they said it but certainly the
idea that there are that what appear to
be opposites are in fact not opposites
at all but are in fact you know you know
that the more you push in one direction
the more that goes in that direction
where you going there's in the same
would he would he would talk the same
about things like free will saying you
know what it depends if you look at in
one way it's free world look at the
other way it's total determinism if you
push past that determiners and looks
like pretty well there's a constant
flipping of these of these two poles so
and he talks about women are lost in the
same way as peace and does for the male
and the female he talks about those
archetypes of the woman being unknowable
and dark and represented by the earth
and the underground you know and and and
she'll be damned if she'll be known you
know the women are always unknowable in
his his view and and men are much more
but he always divides the world into
spiky and wiggly I think you know and
and and the men are much more spiky you
know can you didn't demonstrate exactly
this and this and this and sort of and
women are much more like water and the
idea that they're much more and these
sort of ideas of gender these are kind
of taboo ideas in the sort of you know
on the left in politics today the idea
that there can be some kind of
fundamental difference in the male and
female principles but clearly it was a
union to that extent and you know and
it's a real shame those kind of things
there unsayable it's one of the reasons
that we seem to have lost our wires as a
thinking culture because once we start
to deny the way their different ways men
and women put their world together you
know and say oh well that's you know
that's either irrelevant or it doesn't
exist or worse it's offensive or
oppressive to even suggest the idea
strikes me as a very dangerous denial of
reality I wonder if part of it is due to
the fact that so was pointed out that in
the Western mindset we can see objects
and they're distinct from one another
and in the Eastern mind said especially
Taoism there's more sense of things in
each for your eyes like a flower and a
bee are in essence the same thing as
they can exist without each other really
different ways to see the world I think
he even uses the example somewhere of
Japanese art and argue my phone in a
motel in the Midwest in America where
it's like a fruit bowl it's right in
your face and there's hardly any space
around it
whereas in Japanese art a lot of white
space and just an object in the same
order of human figure is tiny and and
the natural landscape is enormous as
opposed to the man on his horse in
England being in the foreground yeah so
what's the so for me the point is we
find it incredibly difficult to even
hold that idea that polarities can imply
one another rather than one being better
than the other exactly and what I was
gonna ask is so very early on in one of
the Bible lectures Peterson mentions
almost offhand he quite like to do
something around Taoism and there's kind
of the sense for me with Peterson that
he's talked a lot about the West and
Western philosophy but there is
potential to also talk about the East do
you think that's necessary do you think
the
East needs to come in in a new way into
Western culture and the problems were
facing now well absolutely I mean that's
something in was doing you know and you
know and many poets do and people people
like um Eliot you know and I mean there
is a how can you ignore eastern wisdom I
mean it's it's it's a whole found you
know of fascinating ideas once you get
past you know there's rather like
Christianity is like once you get past a
religious iconography and superstructure
and instead of just going over this is
all superstitious nonsense and go yeah
well what's underneath it what what are
these stories trying to tell us you know
which is exactly what Peterson is doing
I'm really what What's it saying what
are these stories what does the Buddhist
story was written what's that trying to
tell us actually you know and it's not
like you know Buddha has got all the
answers what's good is trying to tell us
and what the Buddhist tradition trying
to tell us you know ignore all the you
know all the sort of you know kissing
the gold Buddha - you know all these
things become co-opted by religion and
what Watts was doing was getting to the
root of Eastern religion so what does it
really mean and that's exactly what
Peterson has been doing and answered
Western religion as well but Peterson
has been mainly concentrating on Western
religion is what does this mean and what
are these stories tell us and I think
that's gripping to me you know and
they're so they're both they're both
deep delving under the surface of what
we kind of dismissed as trivia in a way
you know or as was said before
epiphenomenon you know that they're that
these stories have much more profound
meanings than we understand what's
interesting for me about hearing Alan
Watts talk about the shadow is that in
his personal life
you know especially in later years
there's been a lot of talk about his own
personal shadows and this kind of
with with alcohol for example it'd be
great to hear a little bit about you
know I wonder how much of that that
seems like a contradiction to me and
probably a lot of people that he's very
wise incredibly deep thinker and that
his family life is really quite chaotic
it seems compared to Peterson who seems
like a different figure at least
culturally is quite upstanding yeah no
absolutely I mean he's personal life was
disaster I mean he had seven children I
think my three wives yeah certainly the
one he had four children will hated him
til her she died you know I mean and I
mean he he was a womanizer I mean you
know he was that he slept around a lot
and he was a drunk and he took a lot of
drugs I mean there's no he's very
different Buddhism in that sense but
again that's all it's time you know he
was he was pushing out the boundaries of
and everyone drank in the fifties anyway
you know I mean I was pissed all the
time you know so it wasn't quite but he
was an alcoholic let's be honest and he
ended up marrying an alcoholic he was
dragged him down and you know and
clearly he's relationship with you know
who's really I mean I don't want to get
into psychoanalyzing him but he had a
very interesting relationship with his
mother who was clearly the biggest
figure in in his life and he encouraged
all his all his fascination in Eastern
philosophy in a head sort of it started
with her having all these Eastern
artifacts in her home and you know he
was here the mother was a big figure for
him I get the sense listening to both
what Sam Peterson there there's a really
strong performative element to what
they're doing that that I think people
find really compelling well they're both
got tremendous charisma you know that I
mean that's so inevitably that's one of
the things that attracts people to them
but there's also so what is the nature
of that performance well firstly in in
the case of watts he's very funny and
has a wonderful laugh
and what's up and mr. bout peace and
he's also very funny you know if you
watch his sort of some of his lectures
he's hilarious you know and you know
sometimes he comes across as very sort
of you know rather angry Oh white man
you know and he's not tall and he's very
got a great soft side and he's you know
you can see that his students would have
loved him because he's so sort of he's
so sort of mocking and self knocking and
he's very witty so their natural youtube
stars both of them they're both rather
handsome
they're both rather unconventional
looking you know and and and they're
both genius communicators of ideas a
both have rather lovely voices you know
which is also you know I don't like that
you know it's not gonna work Cyril but
they've got and what's has got this
wonderful deep booming English public
school voice which is like wonderful you
know it's like just your really dream
uncle talking to you and and and and and
Peterson has got this very folksy kind
of you know Canadian he does a very good
Kermit impersonation I think I don't
think it sounds like a camera unless he
wants to sound like Kermit bit son but
he has he has that sort of real
approachability you know that that I
think that comes from that comes from a
deep knowledge of your subject actually
you know I think because all right
because I think they both really have
thought through to the very root what it
is they're saying so they're very
careful with what they're saying it has
a tremendous power because so many
people you hear talking and signing
extremely clever but when you think
about it actually what the hell were you
talking about you know and it's actually
I mean I feel that about I won't name
names but you know there are there are a
number of psychologists and thinkers you
know and I'll sit and listen to them
talk I think that's really interesting
then I'll think about a bit more thing
actually it's not really interesting you
know what you've been saying there is
something that sounds like something
that's interesting but actually when you
really examine it it's quite hollow you
know and there's a kind of
there's a kind of posturing to it you
know because there's no real deep
knowledge underneath it and when you
come to Peterson and what so I think
towering figures in their way you know
you can talk about you know Freud and
Jung being towering figures of nature
being towering figure and you know
trouble is that most people don't
understand them you know and don't read
them and they don't have a you know they
don't have a there's no way into them
for an average you know consumer of
information and what what would Pierson
watts provide is is a wonderful conduit
for very you know difficult ideas and
interesting and this is this is
interesting about Peterson and what's as
well is that because they're Mavericks
you know what's was always divided in in
England certainly you know by Oxford and
Cambridge Univ a just thought he was a
joke because he because he was very
understandable you know and people and
everybody understood what he was saying
and they really didn't like that very
much
you know what and likewise Pearson is is
ostracized by many of the at the academy
just as well as sports I mean Moss demon
it didn't even get a degree in the end I
don't think you know they were outside
us and outside has always had the most
interesting take somehow you know but
but but Peterson to is being you know
his own colleagues are sort of disowning
him because he doesn't he doesn't sign
up to their you know their articles of
faith and lots was exactly the same he
didn't sign up to their articles of
faith and thought they were quite
shallow and I was they didn't appreciate
that very much
so Tim just to close we've talked to you
before about Jordan Peterson so I wanted
to take the opportunity to ask about
Alan Watts just in particular so
Peterson has had a huge impact on people
in this kind of post truth radical
relativist world changing the way people
view themselves and their lives what do
you think Watts
can bring right now to to that same
audience look
for meaning looking for some direction
well I think know what what springs to
it is it's partly that's in a strange
way and it is it is slightly different
from what Peters and his sank he was a
great believer in this sort of law of
the law of sort of reverse I think he
called it the reverse principle you know
it is that the more you try the more you
fail the more you look for something
then what you fail to find it you know
which is sort of slightly different from
Peters and he's you know he was and so
what what I think he's got to offers is
this kind of willfulness towards always
living in and they do have something in
common here actually they dislike this
willfulness towards living in the future
you know and that we that our whole
project is about arriving at some
hypothetical future and and that you
know when you get to that future you'll
just be thinking of another future so
you'll never get there you know and he's
a nuts I think in this sort of late
capitalist hyper competitive society
that idea you know very simple and
increasingly popular idea that you know
if you think about the future all the
time you'll never get there and you
would think well that's not Peterson
however Pearson also talks about this he
talks about he talks about the Sermon on
the Mount himself he talks about what
the proper what the proper unit of
thinking about the world is and he also
talks about that consider the lilies of
the field interestingly instead the
proper unit for thinking about is the
day you know so it's not you know
constantly making I mean yes it's
important to have a goal but you know he
oddly enough does he does
[Music]
have a conjoining with with what's there
you know and and as I told you he said I
have to think about the day and he does
he does now I'm not quite sure how you
marry that up you know the idea that
you've got to have this grand goal and
you've got think about the day and I'm
not sure Peterson
you know he's doubtless be out some
seamlessly stitch it together but I you
know I can't quite work out how those
two things coexist but it's he's very
aware of that you know he's very aware
that people gets he's very suspicious of
the grand plan you know and certainly in
terms of the Marxist idea of the grand
plan that you know if you if you set
this vision of idea this ideal vision
ahead of you you know you will be
rewarded with a heaven on earth you know
and he's very he's very suspicious of
that obviously you know so the idea that
there's some kind of place you can get
to so here's so pizzas vision is much
more about you know taking
responsibility for yourself but but I
think he would be very careful in how he
defined responsibility and you know and
and that doesn't mean everything's your
fault you know and and I think that you
know I think I think that's something
what was very concerned was just saying
like it was a very guilt ridden society
the society that he was teaching it in
he was and that's something that the Zen
itself was created really to remove the
guilt of Japanese society when everybody
was worrying about if they gave you know
a beautiful box to their neighbors for
dinner or how much they give back and
they know this whole highly ritualized
Society or whole idea of removing their
anxiety you know and Watts was certainly
involved with us and yeah Peterson is
Pisan inflex on these central ideas but
somehow in my mind and I can't prove it
to you that if you if you follow them
through to the end I think they're
probably serving the same fundamental
truth perfect place to end Tim thank you
very much thank you